<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-26T10:33:12+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Blog++</title><author><name>Blog++</name><email>marco@marcomonteiro.net</email></author><entry><title type="html">How to improve your privacy 1.1 Whatsapp</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/improve-your-privacy-part-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to improve your privacy 1.1  Whatsapp" /><published>2020-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/improve-your-privacy-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/improve-your-privacy-part-2/">&lt;p&gt;Whatsapp is one the most used chat apps, basically everyone uses it. Therefore, even if you don’t like it you’re kinda forced to use it if you want to stay in touch with friends and family. There’s a few setting that you might want to change to make it a bit more private.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 style=&quot;font-weight: 400; font-size: 26px;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt; Understanding Whatsapp&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatsapp is a part of the Facebook family, so that should be a huge red flag right there. However, since 2016 Whatsapp supports end-to-end encryption, that means that nobody on Facebook can read your messages. That’s a wonderful thing. However, Facebook can still access both phones in a conversation and mine some data about them. There’s actually nothing you can do about that besides stop using Whatsapp but that’s not the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 style=&quot;font-weight: 400; font-size: 26px;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt; Turn on two-factor authentication&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very important, if you want to secure your messages this should be enabled. Actually this should be enable everywhere you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The normal way two-factor authentication would work is by sending you a code that would allow you to access the app. But with you opening the app on an average of 50 to 100 times a day that would be impractical. So instead Whatsapp will ask you for a pin every other time and if your phone has fingerprint reader you can make Whatsapp only available after that scan too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 style=&quot;font-weight: 400; font-size: 26px;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt; Turn off cloud backups&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure cloud backups sound amazing, if you’re on Android you just connect to your Google Drive and you’re good to go. But there’s a catch. First you’re getting Whatsapp access to your Google Drive. Second the messages aren’t actually stored securely. This means, if your google account is hacked people will be able to see your messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 style=&quot;font-weight: 400; font-size: 26px;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt; Stop people ouside our contacts from seeing your info&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two things you need to turn off right now. First it’s your public profile the shows your information to everyone and can be mined at will. Second is stop people from outside your contact from adding you to group chats. This will stop those annoying spam messages we get from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 style=&quot;font-weight: 400; font-size: 26px;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt; Stop using whatsapp and move to signal&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is obviously impossible for most people. I know it is form me. I actually only know a few people that uses signal and I don’t know anyone that only uses it. But if you can do that, good for you, you just made it one step forward protecting your data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marco Monteiro</name></author><category term="web privacy, security, standard" /><summary type="html">Whatsapp is one the most used chat apps, basically everyone uses it. Therefore, even if you don’t like it you’re kinda forced to use it if you want to stay in touch with friends and family. There’s a few setting that you might want to change to make it a bit more private.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to improve your privacy 1.0</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/improve-your-privacy-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to improve your privacy 1.0" /><published>2020-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/improve-your-privacy-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/improve-your-privacy-part-1/">&lt;p&gt;For the last 6 months or so I made it my mission to improve my privacy on the web. This article shows you what changes I made so far and what you can also do to protect yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 style=&quot;font-weight: 400; font-size: 26px;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt; Stop using google.com&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first changed I made was stop myself from using google.com. Google tracks everything you do on the web, all your searchs, but most of all, instead of giving you the results that are more relevant based on their SEO score, they give you the result that they think are best for you. This keeps you from seeing different ideas or even getting into websites that might make more sense to what you look for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started using &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/&quot;&gt;DuckDuckGo.com instead&lt;/a&gt;. They don’t track your searches, and most of all you get unbiased results outside the Filter Bubble. They are committed to unbiased search that’s never based on your search history. I even made DuckDuckGo my default search engine on my blog. Give it a go. :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 style=&quot;font-weight: 400; font-size: 26px;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u&gt; Stop Using google Chrome&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google chrome has been my default browser for years now. Before that I used Firefox for a long time but I parted ways with it mostly because it was getting behind in features and it was way slower than Chrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for the same reason I stopped using google.com I thought it was time to give Firefox a try once more. Boy or boy was I impressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firefox is fast, it has all the feature I need in a browser for web-development that I do everyday and in it I installed a bunch of addons that helped further with my quest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Firefox addons I installed realted to privacy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AdBlocker Ultimate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AdBlocker Ultimate is designed with a singular purpose: remove all ads so you can focus your attention on the content you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DuckDuckGo Privacy Essentials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DuckDuckGo Privacy Essentials comes packed with best-in-class privacy essentials and makes browsing in Firefox even faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Escape Online Tracking — automatically block hidden third-party trackers we can find lurking on websites you visit, which stops the companies behind those trackers from collecting and selling your data.
Search Privately — our private search engine comes built-in so you can search the Internet without being tracked.
Enforce Encryption — force sites to use an encrypted (HTTPS) connection where available, protecting your data from prying eyes, like from unwanted snoopers and Internet service providers.
Decode Privacy — each site you visit gets a Privacy Grade (A-F) so you can see how protected you are at a glance, and you can even dig into the details to see who we caught trying to track you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Firefox Multi-Account Containers (This is a must have)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Firefox Multi-Account Containers extension lets you carve out a separate box for each of your online lives – no more opening a different browser just to check your work email! Here is a quick video showing you how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the hood, it separates website storage into tab-specific Containers. Cookies downloaded by one Container are not available to other Containers. With the Firefox Multi-Account Containers extension, you can…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sign in to two different accounts on the same site for example, you could sign in to work email and home email in two different Container tabs. Keep different kinds of browsing far away from each other (for example, you might use one Container tab for managing your Checking Account and a different Container tab for searching for new songs by your favorite band).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoid leaving social-network footprints all over the web (for example, you could use a Container tab for signing in to a social network, and use a different tab for visiting online news sites, keeping your social identity separate from tracking scripts on news sites).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time I’ll tell you all about the changes I made on my phone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marco Monteiro</name></author><category term="web privacy, security, standard" /><summary type="html">For the last 6 months or so I made it my mission to improve my privacy on the web. This article shows you what changes I made so far and what you can also do to protect yourself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Using the Codeigniter 4 standard on your projects with Sublime Text</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/using-codeigniter4-standard-on-your-projects-with-sublime-text/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using the Codeigniter 4 standard on your projects with Sublime Text" /><published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/using-codeigniter4-standard-on-your-projects-with-sublime-text</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/using-codeigniter4-standard-on-your-projects-with-sublime-text/">&lt;p&gt;We moved to Codeigniter 4 for our new projects. Until now, we’ve using phpfmt so everyone in the team can use the same standard while coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However Codeigniter 4 has it’s own standard and it just makes sense for us to move to that new standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this we need:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/squizlabs/PHP_CodeSniffer/&quot;&gt;PHP_CodeSniffer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/codeigniter4/coding-standard&quot;&gt;Codeigniter4-Standard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/FriendsOfPhp/PHP-CS-Fixer&quot;&gt;PHP-CS-Fixer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://packagecontrol.io/packages/Phpcs&quot;&gt;Sublime-phpcs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a few ways we can go about this, but since this was something that we actually need to use on a bunch of projects I going with installing all this globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-php-code-sniffer&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. PHP Code Sniffer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PHP_CodeSniffer requires PHP version 5.4.0 or greater, although individual sniffs may have additional requirements such as external applications and scripts. See the Configuration Options manual page for a list of these requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re using PHP_CodeSniffer as part of a team, or you’re running it on a CI server, you may want to configure your project’s settings using a configuration file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ composer global require &quot;squizlabs/php_codesniffer=*&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-codeigniter-4---coding-standard&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Codeigniter 4 - Coding Standard&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using composer this can also be installed globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ composer global require codeigniter4/codeigniter4-standard
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-php-cs-fixer&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. PHP CS Fixer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install PHP CS Fixer, install Composer and issue the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ composer global require friendsofphp/php-cs-fixer
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then make sure you have the global Composer binaries directory in your PATH. This directory is platform-dependent, see Composer documentation for details. Example for some Unix systems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ export PATH=&quot;$PATH:$HOME/.composer/vendor/bin&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-sublime-phpcs-package&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Sublime-phpcs package&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open your sublime text and install this package. After that you want to to open the user setting and change the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should pay special attention to the following setting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&quot;phpcs_executable_path&quot;: &quot;/home/marco/.config/composer/vendor/squizlabs/php_codesniffer/bin/phpcs&quot;,
&quot;phpcs_additional_args&quot;: {
    &quot;--standard&quot;: &quot;/home/marco/.config/composer/vendor/codeigniter4/codeigniter4-standard/CodeIgniter4&quot;,
    &quot;-n&quot;: &quot;&quot;
},
&quot;php_cs_fixer_executable_path&quot;: &quot;/home/marco/.config/composer/vendor/friendsofphp/php-cs-fixer/php-cs-fixer&quot;,
&quot;phpcbf_executable_path&quot;: &quot;/home/marco/.config/composer/vendor/squizlabs/php_codesniffer/bin/phpcbf&quot;,
&quot;phpcbf_additional_args&quot;: {
    &quot;--standard&quot;: &quot;/home/marco/.config/composer/vendor/codeigniter4/codeigniter4-standard/CodeIgniter4&quot;,
    &quot;-n&quot;: &quot;&quot;
},
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paths should be the ones you have on your system. I’m on linux, so the composer installed globally are in my .config. If you’re on windows or mac your paths might differ.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marco Monteiro</name></author><category term="blog,codeigniter 4, standard" /><summary type="html">We moved to Codeigniter 4 for our new projects. Until now, we’ve using phpfmt so everyone in the team can use the same standard while coding.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moved my blog to jekyll and hosting it on github</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/moved-my-blog-to-jekyll-hosted-in-github/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moved my blog to jekyll and hosting it on github" /><published>2020-08-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/moved-my-blog-to-jekyll-hosted-in-github</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/moved-my-blog-to-jekyll-hosted-in-github/">&lt;p&gt;I had my blog on wardrobe and using a normal shared hosting for a long time. Worked out great for my blog and website. However later I’ve been playing more and more with static website generators and see what can be done with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind I decided to move both my website and blog to github hosting, for freeI might say and just use Jekyll to generate the static websites that I need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blog is really fast now, and everything works exactly like I want it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I even used duckduckgo for the search functionality and it works amazing and with that I’m even supporting a really cool project.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marco Monteiro</name></author><category term="blog,2020" /><summary type="html">I had my blog on wardrobe and using a normal shared hosting for a long time. Worked out great for my blog and website. However later I’ve been playing more and more with static website generators and see what can be done with them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to setup Codeigniter 4</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/how-to-setup-codeigniter-4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to setup Codeigniter 4" /><published>2020-07-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/how-to-setup-codeigniter-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/how-to-setup-codeigniter-4/">&lt;p&gt;I started a brand new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC9HQjernJPHN-RoKMwtYQ4w&quot;&gt;youtube channel&lt;/a&gt;. It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC9HQjernJPHN-RoKMwtYQ4w&quot;&gt;TIL Things&lt;/a&gt;. As in Today I Learned Things. The idea is to share kinda the same thing I normally do here but in a video format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start things, I decided to do a video series about Codeigniter 4, from how to install it, how it works and building a small blog application with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the first video. I hope you can enjoy it and if you do please consider liking and subscribing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tSdbT0GMEqU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the code that will exist in these series will live in the following github repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mpmont/ci4-screencasts&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marco Monteiro</name></author><category term="codeigniter 4, docker, linux, php,2020" /><summary type="html">I started a brand new youtube channel. It’s called TIL Things. As in Today I Learned Things. The idea is to share kinda the same thing I normally do here but in a video format.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My work setup - 2020 update</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/my-work-setup-2020-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My work setup - 2020 update" /><published>2020-06-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/my-work-setup-2020-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/my-work-setup-2020-update/">&lt;p&gt;It’s mid 2020, Ubuntu has a new LTS release and with it its time to try a few things and actually update. As you know I’m now using Pop!OS a distro based on Ubuntu. I already wrote an entire blog post about it. Now I’m going to show you the actual tools I use at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;operating-system&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OPERATING SYSTEM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pop.system76.com/&quot;&gt;Pop!OS&lt;/a&gt; is designed for fast navigation, easy workspace organization, and fluid, convenient workflow. Your operating system should encourage discovery, not obstruct it. It uses gnome by default and that’s what I use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the look of it when I load it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/mXV0OZx.png&quot; alt=&quot;Desktop&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the theme and icons that I’m using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/WDLwzXl.png&quot; alt=&quot;neofetch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;terminal-emulator&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TERMINAL EMULATOR&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see from that neofech print, I’m now using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/alacritty/alacritty&quot;&gt;Alacritty&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve been a long term terminator user, but ever since I discovered Alacritty I never went back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/ABbhg8a.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alacritty&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alacritty is a terminal emulator with a strong focus on simplicity and performance. With such a strong focus on performance, included features are carefully considered and you can always expect Alacritty to be blazingly fast. By making sane choices for defaults, Alacritty requires no additional setup. However, it does allow configuration of many aspects of the terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software is considered to be at a beta level of readiness – there are a few missing features and bugs to be fixed, but it is already used by many as a daily driver, Including me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;text-editor&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TEXT EDITOR&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes I’m still using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sublimetext.com/&quot;&gt;Sublime Text 3&lt;/a&gt; and I don’t plan on changing that. However, when I need to use a terminal based text editor I’m actually using Micro. &lt;a href=&quot;https://micro-editor.github.io&quot;&gt;Micro&lt;/a&gt; is easy to use ans it’s number one feature is being easy to install (it’s just a static binary with no dependencies) and easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/qDwzk0n.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sublime and micro&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uses a simple json format to configure your options and rebind keys to your liking. If you need more power, you can use Lua to configure the editor further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SHELL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a ZSH user for so long, used it for probably 6 years. However at the start of this year and started to try something new. The one I ended up with was fish. And then I obviously installed oh-my-fish. &lt;a href=&quot;https://fishshell.com/&quot;&gt;Fish&lt;/a&gt; is a smart and user-friendly command line shell for Linux, macOS, and the rest of the family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/VPaI1c1.png&quot; alt=&quot;A simple LS&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dot-files&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.DOT FILES&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to take a look at my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mpmont/dotFiles&quot;&gt;dotfiles&lt;/a&gt;? Sure I have them all on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mpmont/dotFiles&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;. Get on it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marco Monteiro</name></author><category term="alacritty, fish, linux, micro, popOS, shell, sublime text, work,2020" /><summary type="html">It’s mid 2020, Ubuntu has a new LTS release and with it its time to try a few things and actually update. As you know I’m now using Pop!OS a distro based on Ubuntu. I already wrote an entire blog post about it. Now I’m going to show you the actual tools I use at the moment.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I moved from Ubuntu to PopOS!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/why-i-moved-from-ubuntu-to-popos!/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I moved from Ubuntu to PopOS!" /><published>2020-06-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/why-i-moved-from-ubuntu-to-popos!</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/why-i-moved-from-ubuntu-to-popos!/">&lt;p&gt;PopOS! really made a big splash with its new 20.04 release and many long terms Ubuntu users like myself are now considering the change or actually changing. And there’s good reason why this is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who don’t know PopOs! is actually based on Ubuntu, so you might be like: - If that’s the case why don’t you just stick with Ubuntu? - That’s a good question. So here’s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-made-from-the-guys-at-system76&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IT’S MADE FROM THE GUYS AT SYSTEM76&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know what &lt;a href=&quot;https://system76.com/&quot;&gt;system76&lt;/a&gt; is, they are a hardware company that is focussed on shipping their laptops and desktops with linux based systems. So much so, that they started their own distro to make the experience better. Why is this important? Because their distro is focussed on the hardware. Not that I ever had anything bad to say against Canonical, I just like system76 more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;they-dont-change-the-default-gnome-experience&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THEY DON’T CHANGE THE DEFAULT GNOME EXPERIENCE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things that always bothered me in Ubuntu was the changes they make to gnome. Specially because they only do it for one reason, for the desktop environment to look more like the one that was created by them, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unity_%28user_interface%29&quot;&gt;Unity&lt;/a&gt;. And we all hated Unity right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hated this so much that my Ubuntu installs on both personal desktop, laptop and work computer always have the default &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnome.org/&quot;&gt;gnome&lt;/a&gt; desktop instaled instead of the one that comes with Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;flatpak&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FLATPAK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never had anything against snaps. Canonical had a problem at the time and they solved it. However, now that we have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flatpak.org/&quot;&gt;flatpaks&lt;/a&gt; that have become more and more popular I really don’t see the point of using &lt;a href=&quot;https://snapcraft.io/&quot;&gt;snaps&lt;/a&gt;. PopOs! has the same philosophy and they ship their system already supporting flatpaks and even the shop that comes with it supports it, giving me the choice if I want to install a .deb or a flatpak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;disk-encryption-by-default&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISK ENCRYPTION BY DEFAULT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PopOs! takes your privacy and files very seriously, that’s why during the instalation proccess you actually have to opt out the disk encryption if that’s something you don’t want. But why wouldn’t you want it right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;window-tiling-inside-gnome&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WINDOW TILING INSIDE GNOME&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;438&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-fltwBKsMY0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things that had me intrigged even when popOs! was still in beta was the option to tile windows inside gnome. I always had a passion about window managers like i3 and others. Just never made the change because there’s a lot of stuff I want from a desktop environment like gnome that a window manager doesn’t have. When they started showing the demos about this feature I was blown away. Sure you can even install it on ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;steam-and-litrus&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STEAM AND LITRUS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not that I do any more gaming besides minecraft on Linux, but if you plan on doing so, popOs! comes with almost everything pre-configured for you so that your gaming experience can be as easy as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marco Monteiro</name></author><category term="20.04, 2020, lts, popOs!,linux" /><summary type="html">PopOS! really made a big splash with its new 20.04 release and many long terms Ubuntu users like myself are now considering the change or actually changing. And there’s good reason why this is happening.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">$ exa A modern replacement for ls</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/meet-exa-a-modern-replacement-for-ls/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="$ exa A modern replacement for ls" /><published>2020-04-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/meet-exa-a-modern-replacement-for-ls</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/meet-exa-a-modern-replacement-for-ls/">&lt;p&gt;You list files hundreds of times a day. Why spend your time squinting at black and white text?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;exa is an improved file lister with more features and better defaults. It uses colours to distinguish file types and metadata. It knows about symlinks, extended attributes, and Git. And it’s small, fast, and just one single binary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;exa is written in Rust. So you’ll need that first in case you don’t already have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run the following command (assuming you have curl installedo on your system) to get started with the installation of Rust in your ubuntu based server/pc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ curl https://sh.rustup.rs -sSf | sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you need to download the lattest version of exa. Head on to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ogham/exa/releases&quot;&gt;their github page&lt;/a&gt; and download the lattest version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just copy the download link and download the zip using wget, for example with the v0.9.0 you can download the binary with the following command (you can switch to a temporary directory and download the zip in there):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# You should check your own version of this.
$ wget -c https://github.com/ogham/exa/releases/download/v0.9.0/exa-linux-x86_64-0.8.0.zip
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, unzip the binary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ unzip exa-linux-x86_64-0.8.0.zip
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The zip contains a single file, namely the binary exa-linux-x86_64. So the last step is to move it to the bin directory of the local user so it will be accesible later in the cli as exa with the following instruction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo mv exa-linux-x86_64 /usr/local/bin/exa
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use this all you need is to type exa on your terminal. However what you can do to make the change even more perminante is to alias ls to axa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do that I went to my .zshrc file and added the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;alias ls='exa --long --header --git'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way you can use your ls command like you always did and it will be translated into exa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/VXTYKQl.png&quot; alt=&quot;exa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exa supports the following main features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colours&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different types of file and data will be coloured differently, and the user and group columns will be highlighted for the current user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All the information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;exa can display a file’s extended attributes, as well as standard filesystem information such as the inode, the number of blocks, and a file’s various dates and times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s fast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;exa queries files in parallel, giving you performance on par with ls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tree view&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is the standard tree tool built-in, but it’ll show you your files’ information alongside the hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Git support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View the staged and unstaged status of every file, right there in the standard view. Also works in tree view for a high-level overview of your repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wide view&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many columns can you display in your terminal at once? How many do you need?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marco Monteiro</name></author><category term="2020,linux,terminal,ubuntu" /><summary type="html">You list files hundreds of times a day. Why spend your time squinting at black and white text?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Covid-19 made us more productive</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/covid-19-made-us-more-productive/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Covid-19 made us more productive" /><published>2020-04-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/covid-19-made-us-more-productive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/covid-19-made-us-more-productive/">&lt;p&gt;I manage a small team of 6 including myself. I mostly do quality control stuff at work and I’ve been programming less and less in the past few months, mainly because I’m more involved in the project management side of things. However, there were always a few things that I knew we could do better and wanted to change but it was really hard to find the right time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then COVID-19 came about and we had to change and adapt to this new reality. Specially with everyone now working from home. There were 3 things that I wanted to change but still didn’t have the time to. Let’s talk about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;strong&gt;**PROJECT MANAGEMENT**&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things that I talked about with management many times was my difficult to do project management, specially because the tools we were using were not built to do project management for real.
We were basically using a mix of google docs spreadsheets, gitlab issues and boards to get us going. I know it makes no sense but it was perfect when it was just me. At the time Gitlab was the right choice since I could create kanban boards and use them to manage my project.
Problem is, when you do this with several projects you get sidetracked and just can’t get the big picture on how things are going with all of your projects. This is something extremely important specially when everyone is working remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to use Clickup. It has everything we need at the moment and more. You can create your own dashboards with project status and tasks per user. You can create boards per project and calendar view among other things. Most important of all it has gitlab integration.
Want to know more? I found this YouTube video about it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;370&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LibP_KTUK8I&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a big bost in our productivity, it makes my life way easier when I have to answer to management on how the projects are going. I can answer problems easily and the team feels more productive because they can look at all their tasks in one place, despite the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;strong&gt;**COMMUNICATION**&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other problem we had was how we communicated at the office. We used to use fucking whatsapp and I always hated it. Now we finally changed to slack and my life is so much better now. I have channels like I used to have on IRC and I can create threads there. I really love threads. And better than that, I can have my work related chats all in one place. I don’t need to have my family group chats mixed up with my work stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;370&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/276Sz-fcxck&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;strong&gt;**CONTINUOUS INTEGRATION**&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something that I still plan on getting better during this quarantine time. I think I’m able to make things work way better with gitlab, docker and our production servers. If you don’t know what I’m talking about you can read more about it &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.gitlab.com/stages-devops-lifecycle/continuous-integration/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://about.gitlab.com/images/ci/ci-cd-test-deploy-illustration_2x.png&quot; alt=&quot;CI — Gitlab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was everything great with this change into a completly remote work environment? No, far from it. The lack of personal relationships at the office, the solitude of being inside 24/7 and time management were a big problem at first. When it started I worked way more at home than I did at the office, mostly because I worked since I woke up until I went to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days I try to do my normal schedule and work 9 to 5 even though I’m still in front of the computer most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marco Monteiro</name></author><category term="2020,covid-19,productivity,quarantine" /><summary type="html">I manage a small team of 6 including myself. I mostly do quality control stuff at work and I’ve been programming less and less in the past few months, mainly because I’m more involved in the project management side of things. However, there were always a few things that I knew we could do better and wanted to change but it was really hard to find the right time.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Installing SQLsrv extension for PHP 7.2 on Ubuntu 18.04 LTS</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/post/installing-sqlsrv-extension-for-php-7.2-on-ubuntu-18.04-lts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Installing SQLsrv extension for PHP 7.2 on Ubuntu 18.04 LTS" /><published>2020-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/post/installing-sqlsrv-extension-for-php-7.2-on-ubuntu-18.04-lts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/post/installing-sqlsrv-extension-for-php-7.2-on-ubuntu-18.04-lts/">&lt;p&gt;One of our windows servers got updated to a more recent version of windows and SQLServer. Until then I was using the msSQL extension and was still on PHP 5.6 on our intranet at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this update I decided to upgrade our servers too and move to PHP 7.2 and obviously to the SQLsrv extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume that you already have PHP install and apache, so after that you should just do the following to get your microsoft packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On your server type the following commands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl -s https://packages.microsoft.com/keys/microsoft.asc | sudo apt-key add -
sudo bash -c &quot;curl -s https://packages.microsoft.com/config/ubuntu/18.04/prod.list &amp;gt; /etc/apt/sources.list.d/mssql-release.list&quot;
sudo apt-get update
sudo ACCEPT_EULA=Y apt-get -y install msodbcsql17 mssql-tools
sudo apt-get -y install unixodbc-dev
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this, you most likelly don’t have the  the pecl7.X-sp command working. To solve this I did the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get -y install gcc g++ make autoconf libc-dev pkg-config
sudo apt-get install php-pear php-dev
sudo pecl install sqlsrv
sudo pecl install pdo_sqlsrv
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this all you need to do is create the necessary .ini file so that PHP can do its magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo bash -c &quot;echo extension=sqlsrv.so &amp;gt; /etc/php/7.2/mods-available/sqlsrv.ini&quot;
sudo ln -s /etc/php/7.2/mods-available/sqlsrv.ini /etc/php/7.2/apache2/conf.d/sqlsrv.ini
sudo ln -s /etc/php/7.2/mods-available/sqlsrv.ini /etc/php/7.2/cli/conf.d/sqlsrv.ini
sudo bash -c &quot;echo extension=pdo_sqlsrv.so &amp;gt; /etc/php/7.2/mods-available/pdo_sqlsrv.ini&quot;
sudo ln -s /etc/php/7.2/mods-available/pdo_sqlsrv.ini /etc/php/7.2/apache2/conf.d/pdo_sqlsrv.ini
sudo ln -s /etc/php/7.2/mods-available/pdo_sqlsrv.ini /etc/php/7.2/cli/conf.d/pdo_sqlsrv.ini
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this all you need to do is restart your apache:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo service apache2 restart
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Marco Monteiro</name></author><category term="2020,apache,linux,mssql,php,sqlsrv,ubuntu" /><summary type="html">One of our windows servers got updated to a more recent version of windows and SQLServer. Until then I was using the msSQL extension and was still on PHP 5.6 on our intranet at work.</summary></entry></feed>